# Louis Sharrock

l.sharrock@lancaster.ac.uk | https://louissharrock.github.io/

271 High Kingsdown Bristol, UK BS2 8DF +44 7544 391601

#### **SUMMARY**

I am a senior research associate in statistical machine learning at Lancaster University. Prior to this, I was a HIMR Data Science Research Fellow at the University of Bristol. I obtained my PhD in Statistics from Imperial College London, supervised by Dr Nikolas Kantas and Professor Dan Crisan, and a BA in Mathematics from the University of Cambridge.

My research interests lie at the intersection of machine learning, optimisation, and computational statistics. My current research focuses on the development of parameter-free methods for scalable Bayesian inference, the use of score-based diffusion models for simulation based inference, and the design of efficient methods for online parameter estimation in interacting particle systems.

#### RESEARCH EMPLOYMENT

2022 - Present Senior Research Associate in Statistical Machine Learning

Department of Mathematics and Statistics, Lancaster University

2022 - Present Research Consultant

Heilbronn Institute for Mathematical Research

2022 - Present Honorary Senior Research Associate

School of Mathematics, University of Bristol

2022 Heilbronn Data Science Research Fellow

Department of Mathematics, University of Bristol

#### **EDUCATION**

2018 - 2022 PhD in Statistics

Department of Mathematics, Imperial College London

Thesis: "On the Theory and Applications of Stochastic Gradient Descent in

Continuous Time."

Supervisor: Dr Nikolas Kantas, Professor Dan Crisan.

2017 - 2018 MRes in Mathematics (Distinction - 93%)

Department of Mathematics, Imperial College London

Thesis: "Large Scale Inference with Applications to Environmental Monitoring."

(91%)

Supervisor: Dr Nikolas Kantas.

2016 - 2017 MSc in Statistics (Distinction - 80%)

Department of Mathematics, Imperial College London

Thesis: "An Application of Bayesian Networks to Yield Prediction in Portuguese

Viticulture." (91%)

Supervisor: Dr Ben Calderhead.

2013 - 2016 BA (Hons) in Mathematics (2.1)

Emmanuel College, University of Cambridge

CATAM Computational Project: 98% (2nd year), 95% (3rd year).

## **PUBLICATIONS**

2023	L. Sharrock, L. Mackey, C. Nemeth (2023). Learning Rate Free Bayesian Inference in Constrained Domains. To appear in Proceedings of the 37th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS). arXiv.
2023	L. Sharrock, C. Nemeth (2023). Coin Sampling: Gradient-Based Bayesian Inference without Learning Rates. <i>Proceedings of the 40th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)</i> , Hawaii. <u>Link</u> .
2023	L. Sharrock, N. Kantas., P. Parpas, and G.A. Pavliotis (2023). Online Parameter Estimation for the Stochastic McKean-Vlasov Equation. <i>Stochastic Process and their Applications</i> , 162, 481-546. <u>DOI</u> .
2023	L. Sharrock and N. Kantas (2023). Two Timescale Stochastic Gradient Descent in Continuous Time with Applications to Joint Online Parameter Estimation and Optimal Sensor Placement. <i>Bernoulli</i> , 29(2), 1137-1165. <b>DOI</b> .
2023	J. Simons*, <b>L. Sharrock*</b> , S. Liu, M. Beaumont (2023). Neural Score Estimation: Likelihood Free Inference with Conditional Score Based Diffusions. <i>Proceedings of the 5th Symposium on Advances in Approximate Bayesian Inference (AABI)</i> , Hawaii. <u>Link.</u>
2022	L. Sharrock (2022). Two-Timescale Stochastic Approximation for Bilevel Optimisation Problems in Continuous-Time Models. <i>Proceedings of the 39th International Conference for Machine Learning: Workshop on Continuous Time Methods for Machine Learning (ICML)</i> , Online. <u>Link</u> .
2022	<b>L. Sharrock</b> and N. Kantas (2022). Joint Online Parameter Estimation and Optimal Sensor Placement for the Partially Observed Stochastic Advection-Diffusion Equation. <i>SIAM / ASA Journal on Uncertainty Quantification</i> , 10(1), 55-95. <b>DOI</b> .
2022	L. Sharrock (2022). On the Theory and Applications of Stochastic Gradient Descent in Continuous Time. <i>PhD Thesis, Imperial College London</i> . <u>Link</u>
2021	C. Leadbeater*, <b>L. Sharrock*</b> , B. Coyle, and M. Benedetti (2021). F-Divergences and Cost Function Locality in Generative Modelling with Quantum Circuits. <i>Entropy</i> , 23(10), 1281-1304. <b>DOI</b> .
In Submission	
2023	<b>L. Sharrock</b> , D. Dodd, C. Nemeth (2023). CoinEM: Tuning-Free Particle-Based Variational Inference For Latent Variable Models. <i>In submission to AISTATS</i> 2024. <u>arXiv</u> .
In Preparation	
2023	L. Sharrock, N. Kantas., P. Parpas, and G.A. Pavliotis (2023) . "Online Learning in Interacting Particle Systems using Single Trajectory Data." <i>In preparation for submission to Stats and Computing.</i>
2023	L. Sharrock*, J. Simons*, S. Liu, M. Beaumont (2022). "Sequential Neural Score Estimation: Likelihood-Free Inference with Conditional Score Based Diffusions." In preparation for submission to TMLR. <u>arXiv</u> .

PRESENTATIONS	

Invited Talks	
Jul 2024	Coin Sampling: Parameter-Rate Optimisation on the Space of Probability Measures, 25th International Symposium on Mathematical Programming (Montreal, Canada).
Mar 2024	Online Learning in McKean-Vlasov SDEs and Interacting Particle Systems using Single Trajectory Data, SIAM Conference on Uncertainty Quantification (Trieste, Italy).
Oct 2023	Sequential Neural Score Estimation: Likelihood-Free Inference with Conditional Score Based Diffusion Models, <i>Alan Turing Institute: Seminars on Simulation Based Science</i> (Online).
Jun 2023	Mirrors and Coins: Learning-Rate Free Methods for Bayesian Inference in Constrained Domains, OxCSML Seminar, Oxford University (Oxford, UK).
Jun 2023	Online Learning in McKean-Vlasov SDEs and Interacting Particle Systems using Single Trajectory Data, Stochastic Analysis and Algorithms Seminar, Wuhan University (Online).
Mar 2023	Coin Sampling: Gradient-Based Bayesian Inference without Learning Rates, BayesComp 2023 (Levi, Finland).
Feb 2023	Particle Based Methods for Online Parameter Estimation in McKean-Vlasov Stochastic Differential Equations, SIAM Conference on Computational Science and Engineering (Amsterdam, The Netherlands).
Mar 2022	Parameter Estimation for the McKean Stochastic Differential Equation, Computational Statistics and Machine Learning Seminars, Lancaster University (Lancaster, UK).
Mar 2022	Parameter Estimation for Weakly Interacting Particle Systems and Stochastic McKean-Vlasov Processes, <i>Statistics Seminars, University of Bristol</i> (Bristol, UK).
Contributed Ta	alks and Poster Presentations
Jun 2023	Coin Sampling: Gradient-Based Bayesian Inference without Learning Rates, Workshop on Distance Based Methods in Machine Learning, University College London (London, UK).
Aug 2021	Parameter Estimation for Stochastic McKean-Vlasov Equations, $Joint\ Statistical\ Meetings\ 2021\ (Online)$ .
Jul 2021	Parameter Estimation for Weakly Interacting Particle Systems and Stochastic McKean-Vlasov Processes, <i>Bernoulli-IMS 10th World Congress in Probability and Statistics</i> (Online).
Jun 2020	Two Timescale Stochastic Gradient Descent in Continuous Time with Applications to Joint Online Parameter Estimation and Optimal Sensor Placement, <i>Mathematics of Data Science Conference</i> (Online)

Nov 2019	Large Scale Inference with Applications to Environmental Monitoring, MATHMET 2019 International Conference (Lisbon, Portugal).
Nov 2019	Joint Online Parameter Estimation and Optimal Sensor Placement with Applications to a Stochastic Advection Diffusion Equation, Conference on Big Data, Data Assimilation and Uncertainty Quantification, Institut Henri Poincaré (Paris, France).
Nov 2019	Large Scale Inference and Optimal Design with Applications to Environmental Monitoring, <i>The Postgraduate Institute Conference, National Physical Laboratory</i> (Teddington, UK).
Jul 2019	Online Parameter Estimation in Continuous Time with Applications to a Stochastic Advection Diffusion Equation, Workshop on Stochastic Parameterisations and Their Use in Data Assimilation, Imperial College London (London, UK).
May 2019	Large Scale Inference with Applications to Environmental Monitoring, Postgraduate Forum, Imperial College London (London, UK).
Nov 2018	An Application of Bayesian Networks to Yield Prediction in Portuguese Viticulture, 6th Annual BayesiaLab Conference (Chicago, USA).

PRIZES, AWARDS, AND FUNDING Prizes and Awards		
2023	Yael Dowker Prize (proxime accessit). Department of Mathematics, Imperial College London. Prize awarded for the best Maths PhD Thesis.	
2020	<b>Doris Chen Merit Award.</b> Department of Mathematics, Imperial College London. Prize awarded to recognise exceptional early promise, progress and achievement in PhD studies.	
2019	Best Poster Prize, Statistics Section, Postgraduate Forum. Department of Mathematics, Imperial College London.	
2018	MRes Student of The Year. Centre for Doctoral Training, Mathematics of Planet Earth, Imperial College London. Prize awarded to the best overall student on the course.	
2013 - 2016	<b>BP STEM Scholarship.</b> University of Cambridge. National scholarship awarded to ten STEM students each year.	
2013	Rowley Mainhood Award. Emmanuel College, University of Cambridge. Award recognising outstanding achievement in pre-admission examinations.	

Research Funding		
2023	G-Research Early Career Research Grant. G-Research, London. A grant	
	for early career researchers, awarded to enable high quality, innovative research in a quantitative discipline.	
2021	Doris Chen Mobility Fund. Department of Mathematics, Imperial College	
	London. A fund providing travel and subsistence for a PhD student with exceptional potential to take their research to another university abroad.	

2018 CliMathParis Travel Grant. Institut Henri Poincaré. A grant to fund attendance at the CliMathParis 2019 conference on big data, data assimilation, and uncertainty quantification.

Warner Prize. Statistics Section, Department of Mathematics, Imperial College London. A prize awarded to support a talented MSc statistics student further develop their research project.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

### 

#### 2023

#### Instructor, School of Mathematics, University of Bristol

- Designed and lectured a new unit on statistical machine learning for third year undergraduates.
- Responsibilities included writing and delivering lectures, supervising computer labs, writing and marking coursework and exams.

#### 2018 - 2021 Graduate Teaching Assistant, Imperial College London

- Supported teaching of undergraduate and postgraduate courses in probability, statistics, and machine learning, including group tutorials and lecturing.
- Courses include *Data and Uncertainty* (Masters), *Computational Statistics* (Masters), *Probability and Statistics* (1st Year Undergraduate).

### 

#### 2014 - 2023 Mathematics Tutor, MyTutor.

- Provided one-to-one tutorials to secondary school, undergraduate, and postgraduate students.
- Completed over 850 hours of lessons, with 175 five-star reviews.
- Awarded 'premium tutor' status to reflect 'impressive expertise and experience'

#### 2014 - 2015 Mathematics Teaching Assistant, STIMULUS.

- Volunteered as a mathematics teaching assistant at a secondary school in Cambridge during undergraduate studies as part of the STIMULUS program.

#### 2014 English Language Teacher, Oxbridge Intercultural Programmes

- Worked as an English language teacher as part of a 4 week residential program at Jinju Health College, South Korea.
- Wrote and delivered English lessons (30 hours per week) to a class of Korean students, achieving highest class average (82%) among all advanced classes on the program.

#### OTHER RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

## 

#### May - Aug 2021 Quantum Machine Learning Scientist, Cambridge Quantum Computing

- Research on new methods for mitigating exponentially vanishing gradients ('barren plateaus') in Quantum Neural Networks.
- Supervised by Marcello Benedetti and Mattia Fiorentini.

Miscellaneous		
2019 - 2021	<ul> <li>Academic Editor, AsiaEdit</li> <li>Edited academic papers, articles, and grant proposals relating to Machine Learning and Statistics.</li> </ul>	
2018 - 2021	Statistics Postgraduate Student Representative, Imperial College London Represented views of students in academic & pastoral matters; organised social activities for staff and students.	
2015	Investment Banking Summer Analyst, Lazard - Prepared pitch-book materials for client meetings, including financial analysis, market research, valuation models, and due diligence.	
ACADEMIC S	SERVICE	
	Workshop Organisation	
Dec 2023	Workshop Co-Organiser. RSS Workshop on Gradient Flows for Sampling, Learning and Inference.	
Mar 2022	Workshop Co-Organiser. Heilbronn Institute of Mathematical Research: Internal Workshop on Neural Networks.	
May 2021	Conference Co-Organiser. 4th Annual MPE CDT Symposium on Wellbeing, Inclusivity, Diversity and Equality in STEM (Virtual).	
Peer Review .		
2023 - present	Reviewer. Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS).	
2022 - present	Reviewer. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society (Series B: Methodology)	
2022 - present	Reviewer. Annales de l'Institut Henri Poincaré.	
2021 - present	Reviewer. Bernoulli.	
OTHER RELEVANT SKILLS		
Computing	Programming Languages. Python, R, MATLAB.	
	Programming Packages. PyTorch, Jax, TensorFlow.	
	Document Markup Languages. LaTeX, HTML.	

Version Control Software. Git.